Finding Aid for the Carey McWilliams Papers LSC.1319
UCLA Library Special Collections
- 3. Division of Immigration and Housing, 1939-1964; 1 box
  - Essay. "Manpower crisis: Mexican immigration, a proposed solution", undated; 2 items. (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Essay. [Rural housing in California], undated; 1 item. (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Notes on the Division of Immigration and Housing, undated; 1 item. (Box 34, Folder 4)
    Typewritten notes on the history of the division.
  - Press release. "Housing shortage in Los Angeles County", undated; 1 item. (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Publicity, 1939-1941; 16 items. (Box 34, Folder 6)
    Press release, newsletter, and newspaper clippings regarding McWilliams in his role at the Division of Immigration and Housing.
  - Report. "Memorandum on housing conditions among migratory workers in California", 1939 March 20; 1 item. (Box 34, Folder 7)
    Report prepared by McWilliams.
  - Address. [The campaign against aliens in America], 1939 April 28; 1 item. (Box 34, Folder 8)
    Text of an address by McWilliams, as Chief of the DIH, before the First National Congress of the Mexican and Spanish American Peoples in the United States, Los Angeles, CA.
  - Report. [Cotton chopping in Madera County], 1939 May 12; 1 item. (Box 34, Folder 9)
    Report prepared by McWilliams, in the form of a letter, to the Hon. Culbert L. Olson regarding a hearing in Madera, CA, on May 9, 1939.
  - Address. "Housing and camps for migrants", 1939 May 18; 5 items. (Box 34, Folder 10)
    Text of an address by McWilliams, as Chief of the DIH, before the California State Conference of Social Work.
  - Report for the Division of Immigration and Housing, 1939 August 20; 2 items. (Box 34, Folder 11)
    General report by McWilliams for the period of January 1, 1939 to July 1, 1939.
  - Report for the Division of Immigration and Housing, 1939 September; 1 item. (Box 34, Folder 12)
    General report by McWilliams.
  - Address. "What are we doing for the interstate migrant", 1939 October 27; 3 items. (Box 34, Folder 13)
    Text of an address by McWilliams, as Chief of the DIH, to the Western Conference on Governmental Problems, San Francisco, CA.
  - Bibliography on immigration and housing issues, 1940-1944; 5 items. (Box 34, Folder 14)
    One letter to C. Read on the compilation of the bibliography, which consists of theses and dissertations accepted by USC from 1910-1939 related to immigration and housing. 38 pages of handwritten notes and typed bibliography.
  - Remarks. [The problem of migratory farm labor in California...], 1940 March 21; 1 item. (Box 34, Folder 15)
    Text of remarks by McWilliams, as Chief of the DIH, before the Migrant Mass Meeting, Los Angeles, CA.
  - Address. "Economics of rural dependency", 1940 May 27; 1 item. (Box 34, Folder 16)
    Text of an address by McWilliams, as Chief of the DIH, before The National Conference of Social Workers in Grand Rapids, MI.
  - Address. "Rural dependency in California", 1940 May 30; 2 items. (Box 34, Folder 17)
    Text of an address by McWilliams, as Chief of the DIH, before The National Conference of Social Work in Grand Rapids, MI.
  - Essay. "Migration and resettlement of the people", 1940 July 8-11; 4 items. (Box 34, Folder 18)
    Text of a paper by McWilliams, as Chief of the DIH, presented at The National Conference on Planning, San Francisco, CA.
  - Testimony before the Tolan Committee, 1940 September 24; 2 items. (Box 34, Folder 19)
    Transcript of McWilliams's testimony regarding migrant housing in San Francisco, CA.
  - Assembly bills, 1941 January 25; 1 item. (Box 34, Folder 20)
  - Testimony before the Select Committee Investigating National Defense Migration, House of Representatives, 1942 March 7; 2 items. (Box 34, Folder 21)
    Transcript of McWilliams's testimony.
  - Report. "Importation of Negro labor to California", 1942 August 10; 1 item. (Box 34, Folder 22)
    Typewritten report prepared by McWilliams.
  - Alien registration reports, 1942 October 3; 1 item. (Box 34, Folder 23)
    Preliminary reports from 1941 from the Immigration and Naturalization Service.
  - Testimony before the Los Angeles County Grand Jury, 1942 October 8; 1 item. (Box 34, Folder 24)
  - Address. "The Department of Industrial Relations", 1942 October 29; 3 items. (Box 34, Folder 25)
    Text of an address by McWilliams, as Chief of the DIH, to the Department of Social Welfare Graduate Students at Berkeley, CA.
  - Miscellaneous letters, 1940-1964; 4 items. (Box 34, Folder 26)
    Letter from Grace McDonald; letters from W.D. Phillips and Mattie Richards Butler regarding McWilliams's tenure at the DIH; one telegram regarding Ray Barry's retirement and McWilliams's response.
- 4. Federal Bureau of Investigation, 1940-1980; 1 box
  This series consists of one folder of correspondence related to McWilliams's Freedom of Information Act requests for information from his CIA and FBI files, and eight folders of photocopied documents from McWilliams's FBI file, arranged in chronological order. The files include reports, transcripts by informants, clippings, and statements of fact related to McWilliams's activities. McWilliams's own research file on the FBI may be found in the general subject files (Subseries 2B, box 73, folder 1).
  - Correspondence, 1976-1980; 15 items. (Box 21, Folder 1)
    Letters to and by Carey McWilliams from Martin Solow (regarding his FBI file), the Department of Justice, the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA), the Naval Investigative Service, and the FBI regarding McWilliams's Freedom of Information Act requests for documents from his FBI and CIA files.
  - File no. 100-2638 (1 of 5), 1940-1944; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - File no. 100-2638 (2 of 5), 1944-1946; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - File no. 100-2638 (3 of 5), 1947-1950; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - File no. 100-2638 (4 of 5), 1951; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - File no. 100-2638 (5 of 5), 1951-1955; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - File no. 100-98442 (1 of 2), 1956-1963; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - File no. 100-98442 (2 of 2), 1964-1972; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Memoranda, 1958-1961; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 9)
    Copies of two documents from McWilliams's FBI files regarding the distribution of Leftist literature to his address.
- 5. Lecture files, 1939-1980; 2 boxes
  This series contains correspondence, publicity materials, receipts, and agency files related to McWilliams's lecture appearances. The correspondence includes lecture offers and letters of thanks. Other materials mentioning McWilliams's lecture appearances may be found in the publicity and criticism files (Series 9), the general subject files (Subseries 2B, box 40, folder 10), and in the general correspondence files (Subseries 2C). Typewritten manuscripts and outlines of actual lectures may be found in the Division of Immigration and Housing files (Series 3), and in the manuscripts subseries for addresses and lectures (Subseries 6A). Files are arranged alphabetically, then chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1949-1957; 34 items. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1962; 10 items. (Box 51, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1963; 31 items. (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1964; 26 items. (Box 51, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1965; 35 items. (Box 51, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1966; 29 items. (Box 51, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1967; 11 items. (Box 51, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1968; 30 items. (Box 51, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1970; 29 items. (Box 51, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1972; 7 items. (Box 51, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1977; 25 items. (Box 51, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence--Re appearances at UC Berkeley and California State College at Bakersfield, 1979-1980; 12 items. (Box 51, Folder 12)
  - Publicity--Promotional leaflets from W. Colston Leigh, undated; 10 items. (Box 51, Folder 13)
  - Publicity--Conference programs, leaflets, and clippings, 1939-1951; 10 items. (Box 51, Folder 14)
  - Publicity--Newspaper clippings, 1953-1963; ca. 60 items. (Box 51, Folder 15)
  - Publicity--Assorted printed materials, 1956-1963; 19 items. (Box 51, Folder 16)
  - Publicity--Assorted printed materials, 1964-1968; 31 items. (Box 51, Folder 17)
  - Publicity--Newspaper clippings, 1964-1968; ca. 50 items. (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - Publicity--Assorted printed materials, 1969-1976; 20 items. (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - Publicity--Newspaper clippings, 1970-1974; 12 items. (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - Publicity--2 leaflets and an activities calendar, 1979; 3 items. (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - Receipts, 1946-1950; 41 items. (Box 52, Folder 5)
  - Receipts and business cards, 1976; 6 items. (Box 52, Folder 6)
  - W. Colston Leigh, Inc.--Correspondence, 1946; 44 items. (Box 52, Folder 7)
  - W. Colston Leigh, Inc.--Correspondence, agreements, notebook, 1947-1952; 13 items. (Box 52, Folder 8)
  - W. Colston Leigh, Inc.--Correspondence, lecture summaries, a signed agreement, and a leaflet, 1958-1959; 11 items. (Box 52, Folder 9)
  - W. Colston Leigh, Inc.--Correspondence, lecture summaries, and a leaflet, 1960; 4 items. (Box 52, Folder 10)
  - W. Colston Leigh, Inc.--Signed contracts, 1960-1965; ca. 100 items. (Box 52, Folder 11)
  - W. Colston Leigh, Inc.--Lecture engagements, 1960-1971; 1 item. (Box 52, Folder 12)
  - W. Colston Leigh, Inc.--Correspondence and lecture summaries, 1962-1963; 14 items. (Box 52, Folder 13)
  - W. Colston Leigh, Inc.--Correspondence and leaflets, 1964-1969; 20 items. (Box 52, Folder 14)
  - W. Colston Leigh, Inc.--Signed contacts, 1966-1971; ca. 100 items. (Box 52, Folder 15)
  - W. Colston Leigh, Inc.--Correspondence and a signed agreement, 1970-1971; 3 items. (Box 52, Folder 16)
  - William B. Feakins, Inc. (1 of 2)--Correspondence and list of engagements, 1943-1946; 61 items. (Box 52, Folder 17)
  - William B. Feakins, Inc. (2 of 2)--Correspondence, 1945-1946; 18 items. (Box 52, Folder 18)
- 6. Manuscripts, 1896-1981; 18 boxes
  This series contains typewritten manuscript drafts and outlines by McWilliams, along with supporting materials. Arranged in subseries A-E as follows:
  A. Addresses and lectures, 1937-1979 (7.5 boxes)
  B. Articles and essays, 1927-1981 (5 boxes)
  C. Book reviews, ca. 1941-1978 (.25 box)
  D. Fiction, ca. 1920s-1948 (.25 box)
  E. Monographs, 1896-1980 (5 boxes).
  Manuscripts composed for McWilliams's role as Chief of the Division of Immigration and Housing can be found in the DIH files (Series 3).
  - 6A. Addresses and lectures, 1937-1979; 7.5 boxes
    This subseries contains drafts and outlines of the many public addresses and lectures given by McWilliams, along with assorted supporting materials. It also includes acceptance speeches for awards. Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - [Academic freedom], undated; 3 items. (Box 53, Folder 1)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address, and two fragments, to be delivered at an undetermined location.
    - Academic freedom, undated; 1 item. (Box 53, Folder 2)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address given in Chicago.
    - [Address], ca. 1949; 1 item. (Box 53, Folder 3)
      Typewritten address before an unidentified audience, on a variety of topics, including: F.O. Matthiessen, the Hollywood Ten, the Bridges case, University of California Loyalty Oaths, and The Education of Carey McWilliams.
    - [Address, Brotherhood Week], undated; 1 item. (Box 53, Folder 4)
      Typewritten outline of an untitled lecture for a Midwest college trip.
    - [Address, Celebration of the golden anniversary of The Capital Times], undated; 3 items. (Box 53, Folder 5)
      Typewritten manuscript on newspapers and their editors and publishers.
    - [Address, Coalition for a Democratic Alternative], 1967 October 10; 1 item. (Box 53, Folder 6)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address delivered in a community church, NY.
    - [Address, The Nation Associates West Coast Conference], ca. 1946; 1 item. (Box 53, Folder 7)
      Typewritten manuscript, untitled, of an address delivered before the first western conference of The Nation Associates.
    - [Address, The Nation dinner], 1978 November 29; 2 items. (Box 53, Folder 8)
      Typewritten manuscript, untitled, of an address delivered before a dinner honoring The Nation and McWilliams's contributions.
    - [Address, Second Annual Conference on American Studies: "The Revolution Heritage in Popular Culture"], 1976 April-May; 11 items. (Box 53, Folder 9)
      Typewritten outline of an address given at San Diego State University. Also includes related letters, receipts, a newsletter, and the conference program and schedule.
    - [The American conversation], 1962 May 7; 1 item. (Box 53, Folder 10)
      Typewritten outline.
    - The American crisis, 1967; 11 items. (Box 53, Folder 11)
      Typewritten outlines.
    - The American political scene (1 of 2), 1960-1964, 1976; 22 items. (Box 53, Folder 12)
      Typewritten outlines and manuscript drafts, to be delivered at various locations.
    - The American political scene (2 of 2), 1968-1970; 17 items. (Box 53, Folder 13)
      Typewritten outline, and various clippings and articles.
    - [American politics], 1963-1966; ca. 25 items. (Box 53, Folder 14)
      Typewritten outline of an untitled address to be delivered at the Economics Club, NY, notes, and clippings.
    - The American scene, ca. 1960; 3 items. (Box 53, Folder 15)
    - The American scene: 1957, ca. 1957; 1 item. (Box 53, Folder 16)
    - America's no. 1 problem, undated; 2 items. (Box 53, Folder 17)
    - America's race problem, undated; 1 item. (Box 53, Folder 18)
    - Are we heading for fascism?, undated; 2 items. (Box 53, Folder 19)
      Typewritten manuscript and outline fragment.
    - Aspects of national defense, undated; 1 item. (Box 53, Folder 20)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address given at an undetermined date and location.
    - Atoms for peace, 1955; 1 item. (Box 53, Folder 21)
      Typewritten outline of an address delivered before The Nation's 90th anniversary conference in New York, NY.
    - [Attitudes towards civil liberties], 1969 December 14; 5 items. (Box 53, Folder 22)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address delivered at an ACLU dinner in Los Angeles, CA.
    - Automation, 1963-1968; 15 items. (Box 53, Folder 23)
      Assorted lecture drafts and outlines from addresses delivered at the College of Marin, Newark State College, and the cities of Flint, MI, San Bernardino, CA, Toronto, and others. Includes variant titles such as "Automation and its effect on human resources," "Automation and the new leisure," and "Automation and abundance.
    - Behind today's The Education of Carey McWilliams, undated; 1 item. (Box 53, Folder 24)
    - The Bicentennial and beyond, 1975 January 27; 2 items. (Box 53, Folder 25)
      Typewritten outlines of an address given at the Cooper Union.
    - The big city press and big city politics, 1959 November 18; 2 items. (Box 53, Folder 26)
      Typewritten outlines for an address for the A.D.A.
    - The Borderlands: let justice make us friends, 1975-1976; 18 items. (Box 54, Folder 1)
      Photocopy of a typewritten manuscript of an address given at the Fronteras 1976 Conference entitled "The International Border" in San Diego. Also includes related correspondence (with Lucy Killea and Larry Goodwyn), the conference proceedings, and assorted printed materials.
    - [C.B. "Beanie" Baldwin], 1975; 4 items. (Box 54, Folder 2)
      Typewritten outline of an address given at Baldwin's memorial, related letters, and an obituary.
    - Carter: after two years, 1979 February 4; 1 item. (Box 54, Folder 3)
    - Chief for a day, undated; 1 item. (Box 54, Folder 4)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address delivered before the ACLU, at an undetermined location.
    - Circumstances, trial, consequences, 1968; 1 item. (Box 54, Folder 5)
    - Citizen response to the disarmament controversy in America, 1962 November 24; 1 item. (Box 54, Folder 6)
      Typewritten manuscript for an address delivered before The National Council for Social Studies, Philadelphia, PA.
    - Civil liberties in the modern world, undated; 3 items. (Box 54, Folder 7)
      Assorted lecture outlines.
    - [Civil liberties lecture notes], 1951-1954; 10 items. (Box 54, Folder 8)
      Untitled manuscript and outline fragments, notes, a program, and clippings.
    - Civil rights: a perspective, 1978; 2 items. (Box 54, Folder 9)
      Typewritten outline of an address, and a related article.
    - Civil rights: sore spot in American democracy, ca. 1957; 2 items. (Box 54, Folder 10)
    - Commencement address, History Department, UC Berkeley, 1979; 15 items. (Box 54, Folder 11)
      Photocopies of typewritten manuscripts, and related correspondence.
    - Comments by Carey McWilliams, 1966 September 30; 7 items. (Box 54, Folder 12)
      Typewritten manuscripts of an address given in response to Vernon Dibble's paper "The garrison society: powerful state and the citizen" at the Conference on National Priorities Problem at Columbia University, New York.
    - [Committee for a Democratic Spain], 1962 December 5; 1 item. (Box 54, Folder 13)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address delivered before the Committee in New York.
    - Community action, undated; 3 items. (Box 54, Folder 14)
      Typewritten lecture outlines on race relations.
    - Consensus politics and the press, 1965 October 19; 6 items. (Box 54, Folder 15)
      Lecture outlines.
    - The continuing tradition of reform journalism, 1970 May 15; 2 items. (Box 54, Folder 16)
      Typewritten outline and manuscript for an address delivered at Penn State.
    - Corruption in U.S. society, ca. 1954; 3 items. (Box 54, Folder 17)
      Two letters signed H.H.W. (H.H. Wilson?), from Princeton, regarding edits to the lecture drafts. Typewritten lecture outline.
    - [The crisis in Vietnam], 1967 August 22; 1 item. (Box 54, Folder 18)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address for Canadian Broadcasting.
    - The crisis of American democracy, undated; 1 item. (Box 54, Folder 19)
    - The crisis of the cities, 1968 April 19; 2 items. (Box 54, Folder 20)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address delivered at Mount Union College.
    - The critical journal of opinion, 1957 October 24; 1 item. (Box 54, Folder 21)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address delivered at Dartmouth College.
    - The cross and the circle, 1946 December 10; 1 item. (Box 54, Folder 22)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address delivered in Montreal, Canada.
    - Current threats to the media, 1970-1971; 3 items. (Box 54, Folder 23)
    - Dare we trust the press?, undated; 1 item. (Box 54, Folder 24)
    - Democracy and the business system, undated; 1 item. (Box 54, Folder 25)
    - Dissent and politics, 1968 March 28; 6 items. (Box 54, Folder 26)
      Typewritten outline of an address delivered at the University of Michigan.
    - [District 1199], 1976 June 24; 2 items. (Box 54, Folder 27)
      Typewritten outline of an address delivered at District 1199's Retirees Banquet about problems facing New York City. Also includes an invitation, and a clipping.
    - Domestic politics in an age of power, undated; 1 item. (Box 55, Folder 1)
    - [Dr. Harold C. Urey], 1955 February 12; 2 items. (Box 55, Folder 2)
      Typewritten draft an address on Dr. Harold C. Urey, delivered on the occasion of his receiving the Joseph Priestley Award.
    - [Ethics and new politics], undated; 1 item. (Box 55, Folder 3)
    - Ethics in an affluent society, 1963-1970; 20 items. (Box 55, Folder 4)
      Typewritten outlines, drafts, and fragments of addresses delivered at different locations.
    - The ethics of affluence, 1962; 3 items. (Box 55, Folder 5)
      Typewritten outlines, and a clipping.
    - The ethics of power, 1968 October 15; 2 items. (Box 55, Folder 6)
      Typewritten outline and draft for an address at N.Y.U. Alternatively titled, "Press power and power pressure."
    - A frank appraisal, 1961 March 23; 1 item. (Box 55, Folder 7)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address on the American press, delivered before the State Teacher's College, Indiana, PA.
    - Freedom and cultural expression, 1953; 2 items. (Box 55, Folder 8)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address delivered at the Nassau Forum. Includes an invitation to the event.
    - [Freedom of association], ca. 1955; 1 item. (Box 55, Folder 9)
      Typewritten outline of an address delivered at Chicago.
    - The genesis of California's cultural climate, 1963 April 6; 3 items. (Box 55, Folder 10)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address delivered in Royce Hall, UCLA.
    - [Geographers and borders], 1971-1978; 29 items. (Box 55, Folder 11)
      Typewritten outline fragment of an address given at the Association of American Geographers 72nd Annual Meeting Special Session: The Mexican American: Papers in Honor of Carey McWilliams, which took place on April 11-14, 1976 in New York, New York. Also contains related correspondence with Richard L. Norstrand and David Hornbeck, conference papers, typed notes about 3 of the papers, and assorted printed materials.
    - [George Polk Award], 1978; 6 items. (Box 55, Folder 12)
      Typewritten manuscript of McWilliams's acceptance speech. Also includes related letters, a leaflet, and a clipping.
    - The great society, 1965-1967; 12 items. (Box 55, Folder 13)
      Assorted typewritten drafts and outlines for addresses delivered at different locations.
    - Growing up in Steamboat, 1975-1978; 33 items. (Box 55, Folder 14)
      Photocopied manuscripts of an address given at the Sun Valley Center for Arts and Humanities' Conference "The Writer and the West," which took place on July 4-8, 1978 in Sun Valley, Idaho. Also includes related correspondence with Richard Hart, another address by McWilliams ("That Awesome Space"), leaflets, a program, clippings, and assorted printed materials.
    - [Heresy], undated; 1 item. (Box 55, Folder 15)
    - Honoring Charles J. Katz, 1979; 8 items. (Box 55, Folder 16)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address given in tribute to Katz. Also includes 2 letters from Katz, and assorted printed materials.
    - Horizons for the independent voter, undated; 2 items. (Box 55, Folder 17)
    - How free is the press in America?, 1958-1959; 5 items. (Box 55, Folder 18)
      Typewritten outlines and clippings.
    - How stands the The Education of Carey McWilliams?, undated; 1 item. (Box 55, Folder 19)
    - Human meaning of change, 1966 October 13; 1 item. (Box 55, Folder 20)
    - [The importance of ideas], 1975-1976; 2 items. (Box 55, Folder 21)
    - In further quest of relevance, 1969-1973; 25 items. (Box 55, Folder 22)
      Typewritten outline, and numerous articles, clippings, and notes on relevance.
    - In quest of relevance (1 of 2), 1969-1970; 10 items. (Box 66, Folder 1)
      Assorted typewritten lecture outlines and drafts.
    - In quest of relevance (2 of 2), 1969-1970; ca. 20 items. (Box 66, Folder 2)
      Assorted typewritten lecture outlines and drafts, and assorted printed materials.
    - Independent voter and the two party system, undated; 1 item. (Box 66, Folder 3)
    - The individual and organized society, 1960-1963; 15 items. (Box 66, Folder 4)
      Assorted lecture drafts, outlines, and manuscripts from addresses delivered at various locations.
    - Individual rights and world upheaval, undated; 1 item. (Box 66, Folder 5)
      Typewritten outline, possibly incomplete.
    - Informal three-dimensional education as a journalist, undated; 1 item. (Box 66, Folder 6)
    - Institutional racism, 1975 April 29; 1 item. (Box 66, Folder 7)
    - Integrating the U.S. into the world, 1962 February 26; 5 items. (Box 66, Folder 8)
      Typewritten outlines and manuscripts for a lecture.
    - Investigative journalism, 1975 April 2; 2 items. (Box 66, Folder 9)
      Typewritten outline for an address delivered at UCLA.